A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John Floyd, 1830-1834
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers of Governor John Floyd, 1830-1834
The Library of Virginia
42665
6.35 cubic feet (14 boxes)
Virginia Governor (1830-1834: Floyd)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Alternate Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reels 6318-6341. Interlibrary Loan copies of microfilm also available.
Miscellaneous Reel 6318 - Box 1, Folders 1-6 (1830 Mar 4-May 29)
Miscellaneous Reel 6319 - Box 1, Folders 7-12 (1830 June 1-Sept 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6320 - Box 2, Folders 1-5 (1830 Oct 1-Nov 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6321 - Box 2, Folders 6-10 (1830 Dec 1-1831 Feb 28)
Miscellaneous Reel 6322 - Box 3, Folders 1-5 (1831 Mar 1-May 17)
Miscellaneous Reel 6323 - Box 3, Folders 6-11 (1831 May 18-July 10)
Miscellaneous Reel 6324 - Box 4, Folders 1-5 (1831 July 11-Aug 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6325 - Box 4, Folders 6-12 (1831 Sept 1-Oct 31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6326 - Box 5, Folders 1-5 (1831 Nov 1-Dec 31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6327 - Box 5, Folders 6-11 (1831 Oct-Dec, Pardons; 1832 Jan 2-31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6328 - Box 6, Folders 1-5 (1832 Feb 1-Mar 20)
Miscellaneous Reel 6329 - Box 6, Folders 6-11 (1832 Mar 21-May 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6330 - Box 7, Folders 1-5 (1832 June 1-July 20)
Miscellaenous Reel 6331 - Box 7, Folders 6-12 (1832 July 21-Sept 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6332 - Box 8, Folders 1-5 (1832 Oct 1-Nov 19)
Miscellaneous Reel 6333 - Box 8, Folders 6-9 (1832 Nov 20-Dec 31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6334 - Box 9, Folders 1-5 (1833 Jan 1-Mar 9)
Miscellaenous Reel 6335 - Box 9, Folders 6-12 (1833 Mar 11-May 31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6336 - Box 10, Folders 1-5 (1833 June 1-July 11)
Miscellaneous Reel 6337 - Box 10, Folders 6-12 (1833 July 12-Sept 30)
Miscellaneous Reel 6338 - Box 11, Folders 1-5 (1833 Oct 1-Nov 24)
Miscellaneous Reel 6339 - Box 11, Folders 6-12 (1833 Nov 25-Dec 31; undated
Miscellaneous Reel 6340 - Box 12, Folders 1-5 (1834 Jan 1-Feb 25)
Miscellaneous Reel 6341 - Box 12, Folders 6-9 (1834 Feb 26-Mar 31; undated)
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905
Biographical Information
John Floyd was born at Floyds Station in Jefferson County, Kentucky, on 24 April 1783 to John Floyd and Jane Buchanan. Educated at Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, Floyd was graduated from the medical department of the University of Pennsylvania in 1806 while under the care of Dr. Benjamin Rush in Philadelphia. Floyd settled in Christiansburg, Montgomery County, Virginia, where he practiced medicine. Serving as a surgeon in the Virginia Militia from 1807 to 1812, Floyd was later appointed surgeon of Lt. Col. James McDowell's Flying Camp during the War of 1812. Floyd received a commission of major, and was appointed brigadier general of the 17th Brigade.
John Floyd's political career began when he was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates to represent Montgomery County in 1814. While only serving one term in the state legislature, Floyd had a long and distinguished tenure in the U.S. House of Representatives where he served from 1817 until 1829. During his time in Congress, Floyd supported President Andrew Jackson's actions in the Great Seminole Debate of 1818-1819, Missouri statehood, and the settling of the Oregon Territory. Following his time in Congress, Floyd was elected as governor of Virginia on 4 March 1830. Floyd served a one-year term and was re-elected to a three-year term as the first governor under the Virginia Constitution of 1829-1830. Floyd's term as governor was noted for its prosperity, but also for the Southampton Insurrection led by the slave Nat Turner on 21 August 1831. During his term as governor, Floyd received all of South Carolina's eleven electoral votes in the Presidential election of 1832 as a result of the Nullification Crisis and that state's discontent with the Tariff of 1828. Floyd suffered a stroke in office, but completed his term of office on 31 March 1834.
John Floyd married Letitia Preston, the daughter of William Preston & Susannah Smith, in 1804. Floyd and his wife had twelve children including John Buchanan Floyd, governor of Virginia from 1849 to 1852 and Secretary of War under President James Buchanan. Floyd died on 17 August 1837 and is buried near Sweetsprings in Monroe County, Virginia. Floyd County, Virginia, was named after John Floyd when the county was created out of Montgomery County on 15 January 1831.
Scope and Content
John Floyd's Executive papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his four years as governor between 4 March 1830 and 31 March 1834. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments & recommendations for state positions; Nat Turner's Rebellion; the Virginia Penitentiary; arms and ammunition; the militia; Revolutionary War bounty land claims; slavery; public improvements; resignations; extraditions; state expenses & revenue; elections; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; contracts; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns & certificates; qualifications; lists; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; opinions; and other sundry items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Executive Papers of Governor John Floyd, 1830-1834
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1808-December 31, 1835, VOL. X, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1892.
Separated Material
Oversized materials have been separated to boxes 13-14.
Contents List
- Executive Papers of Governor John Floyd, 1830-1834., Extent: 14 boxes. (Box 1-14)
  Nat Turner's Rebellion was the most significant historical event during John Floyd's time in office. There is not a great amount of documents related to Nat Turner's Rebellion within John Floyd's Executive Papers, but notable documents include the following: an anonymous letter regarding a reward for the capture of Nat Turner, leader of the insurrection (1831 Aug. 28); a proclamation by Governor Floyd offering a reward for the apprehension of Nat Turner (1831 Sept. 17); a letter from W. C. Parker regarding a physical description of Nat Turner (1831 Sept. 31); a letter from Brig. Gen. Benjamin W. S. Cabell, & other officers of the 11th Brigade, requesting arms & accoutrements necessary for arming two companies of cavalry and two companies of light infantry (1831 Sept. 20); and a resolution of inhabitants of Chesterfield County requesting arms & a patrol to protect against insurrection of slaves (undated).
  The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states. Federal government correspondents include President Andrew Jackson; Martin Van Buren & Edward Livingston, Secretaries of State; Lewis Cass, Secretary of War; Louis McLane, Secretary of the Treasury; & Virginia's senators & representatives in Congress.
  President Andrew Jackson encloses a letter from Samuel D. Ingham, Secretary of the Treasury, regarding debts contracted by Virginia during the Revolutionary War (1831 Mar. 18). Martin Van Buren, Secretary of State, forwards eight sets of the 1st session of the 21st Congress (1831 Mar. 23). Later, Edward Livingston writes to request copies of the Statute Laws of Virginia (1831 July 12). Livingston also writes regarding a resolution of the Senate respecting the militia (1833 Mar. 25) and papers relative to Virginia's northern boundary from the Colonial Office in Great Britain (1833 May 18). As Acting Secretary of State, Daniel Brent transmits three copies of the returns of the Fifth Census (1832 Sept. 10). Louis McLane, Secretary of the Treasury, requests vouchers which bounty land was granted to Joshua McQueen for his service in the Continental Line (1832 Apr. 27). McLane also writes enclosing a copy of the evidence upon which bounty land was granted to the heirs of James Halloway (1832 May 17). On 12 July 1832, McLane encloses a resolution of the House of Representatives to lay before the House copies of statements or returns showing the capital, etc., of the different state banks. In addition, McLane writes requesting the name of the present governor, the date of appointment, & the great seal of the state (1833 July 15). Lastly, McLane requests the numerical strength of the militia (1833 Nov. 30). Lewis Cass, Secretary of War, encloses a letter from Peter Hagner, 3rd Auditor's Office, regarding a book containing settlements made by Andrew Dunscomb as Assistant Commissioner of Army Accounts with the Virginia Continental Line (1833 Nov. 30). Cass later encloses a report of William Gordon, Bounty Land Office, containing a list of persons entitled to land warrants (1833 Nov. 23).
  Philip P. Barbour, writes resigning his seat as a member of the House of Representatives to become District Judge of the United States for the Eastern District (1830 Oct. 15). Littleton W. Tazewell & John Tyler, U.S. Senators, enclose a letter from Samuel D. Ingham, Secretary of the Treasury, transmitting a communication from the Register's Office of the Treasury Department including an abstract of balances due to & from the several states on the adjustment of their accounts with the U.S. by the General Board of Commissioners (1831 Feb. 11). On 1832 October 22, Littleton Tazewell writes resigning his seat as senator. John Tyler also writes Governor Floyd respecting his election to the Senate (1833 Feb. 28). Finally, there are several letters from Virginia's representatives in Congress including Andrew Stevenson, John M. Patton, George Loyall, Joseph W. Chinn, John Y. Mason, & Charles F. Mercer, regarding the unconstitutionality of the Bank of the United States and resolutions of Virginia disapproving the act of the President in withdrawing & withholding the public deposits from the Bank where they have been placed by law (1834 Feb. 24, 25, 26, 28, & Mar. 6).
  The majority of correspondence in John Floyd's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Samuel P. Parsons & Charles S. Morgan, Superintendents of the Penitentiary; James Robertson, Attorney General; Bernard Peyton, Adjutant General; Blair Bolling, Commandant of the Public Guard; George W. Munford, Clerk of the House of Delegates; James E. Heath, Auditor of Public Accounts; and John H. Smith, Agent for Virginia to examine Revolutionary Claims.
  Samuel P. Parsons, Superintendent of the Penitentiary, corresponded with Governor Floyd regarding various issues respecting prisoners and the Virginia Penitentiary. Parsons writes regarding the pardon of Sampson Lawrence (1830 Nov. 4), the release of John Wilcox from solitude (1830 Mar. 18), the manufacture of clothing for the Public Guard (1830 June 1), the removal of Daniel Tolly as 3rd Assistant Keeper (1830 July 18), the release of Henry Hoffman from solitude (1830 Sept. 17), the nomination of William Simpson as 3rd Assistant Keeper & John Duff as 5th Assistant Keeper (1830 Oct. 1), the petition for the pardon of Nathaniel Snelson (1830 Oct. 21), the valuation of transport slaves confined in the Penitentiary (1830 Oct. 30), the case of Sampson Lawrence convicted of 2nd degree murder (1830 Nov. 4), the attendance of Directors of the Penitentiary to meetings of the Board (1831 Apr. 15), permission to use the bricks from the old Powder Magazine near the Penitentiary for other improvements (1831 May 6); the trial of Wyatt King, the only free transport remaining in the Penitentiary (1831 May 10); a house proposed to be erected for John Jacob, an officer of the Penitentiary (1831 May 19); the recommendation of James Shephard as 1st Assistant Keeper, Felix Ferguson as 3rd Assistant Keeper, & Croxton Lumpkin as 4th Assistant Keeper (1831 Sept. 22); and the recommendation of James Nisbett as 5th Assistant Keeper (1832 Feb. 2).
  Charles S. Morgan replaced Parsons as superintendent in March 1832. Morgan wrote Governor Floyd regarding similar issues including the conduct of Frederick Fleming (1832 May 14), the death of Croxton Lampkin, late assistant keeper, & the appointment of Michael Schisler (1832 May 15), the conduct of John T. Owen (1832 June 2), the pardon & immediate discharge of each convict whose term of imprisonment exceeds three months as a result of a cholera outbreak at the Penitentiary (1832 Sept. 29), a report of the deaths at the Penitentiary in the last six months (1832 Sept. 30), the conduct of Thomas Bentley (1832 Dec. 5), the employment of Capt. John Balthrope as inventor of a new plan for gun carriages (1833 Jan. 25), the price of transports from the Penitentiary (1833 Mar. 6), improvements to the Penitentiary including the erection of a hospital, etc. (1833 Apr. 4 & Aug. 9), contracts for repairs at the Penitentiary (1833 July 17), transports at the Penitentiary including their names & ages (1834 Jan. 3), the recommendation of Minus Ward as 5th Assistant Keeper (1834 Mar. 5), the petition for the pardon of Spencer Webb (1834 Mar. 22), and pardons for various convicts at the Penitentiary (1834 Mar. 26). Particularly significant is Morgan's letter enclosing various reports including accounts, the superintendent's report, a table showing the number of prisoners received into the Penitentiary, a table showing the number of prisoners confined in the Penitentiary with their crimes & sentences, a table showing the number of admittances into the hospital, a report of deaths in the Penitentiary, etc. (1833 Nov. 29).
  John Robertson, Attorney General, provides opinions on a slave named Amos condemned by Rockingham County who escaped and was jailed in Ohio (1830 Oct. 23), the publication of the act concerning a convention passed 31 Jan. 1828 & of the new Constitution (1831 July 8), and the commission of James Given as sheriff of Nicholas County (1832 Apr. 8). In addition, Robertson encloses letters of John T. Austin, Attorney General of Massachusetts, & Edward Everett regarding the dissemination of publications of a character to excite insubordination among the slaves of Virginia (1833 May 31).
  Bernard Peyton, Adjutant General, mainly writes regarding arms, ammunition, and the militia. Peyton encloses a letter from Blair Bolling regarding the preparation of four hundred muskets for deliver (1830 May 14), arms to be delivered to the Lexington Arsenal by the Commandant of the 77th Regiment (1830 June 12), powder still remaining at the U.S. Bellona Arsenal in Chesterfield County (1833 Dec. 19), military equipment purchased for Capt. Myers' Troop of Norfolk (1834 Feb. 10), the claim of Byrd Chamberlayne (1834 Mar. 1), and the resignation of Col. Robert W. Carter, 41st Regiment (1834 Mar. 7).
  Blair Bolling, as Commandant of the Public Guard & Superintendent of Public Edifices, writes regarding numerous issues concerning the Public Guard, the Armory, and the Virginia State Capitol. Bolling writes requesting a copy of the proceedings of the Court of Enquiry against him by Ensign Joseph R. Bentley (1830 Mar. 19), the claim of A. Bargamin for the erection of scaffold to clean out the pipe running through the Court of Appeals room (1830 Nov. 29), carpeting for the Senate Chamber & clothing for the Public Guard (1831 Oct. 14), a recommendation of the surgeon of the Public Guard for the discharge of invalids from the corps (1834 Jan. 22), new timber to mount cannon at the Armory (1834 Feb. 3), the proposal of Robert R. Robinson to lease the Boring Mill (1834 Mar. 5); the request of Charles Boze to be discharged from the Public Guard (1834 Mar. 17), repairs to the Treasury Office (1834 Mar. 18), and the agreement between Bragg & Bootwright for the lease of the Boring Mill (1834 Mar. 26).
  George W. Munford, as Clerk of the House of Delegates, often submits legislation to the governor. Noteworthy is an act concerning the Executive Department under the amended Constitution passed 8 February 1831 which defined the role of lieutenant governor & salaries of executive officers (1831 Feb. 8).
  Additionally, Munford transmits the following certificates of election: Wyndham Robertson as a member of the Council (1830 May 29), Lawson Burfoot as Treasurer (1831 Feb. 11, 1833 Mar. 7, & 1834 Mar. 7), Henry St. George Tucker as president and Francis T. Brooke, William H. Cabell, John W. Green, & Dabney Carr as judges of the Court of Appeals (1831 Apr. 11), William C. Rives as senator in Congress (1832 Dec. 10), James E. Heath as Auditor, James Brown as 2nd Auditor, & William Selden as Register of the Land Office (1833 Mar. 7), Benjamin Watkins Leigh as senator in Congress in place of William C. Rives (1834 Feb. 26), and John B. Clopton as judge of the Circuit Superior Court of Law & Chancery for the 7th Judicial Circuit (1834 Feb. 27).
  James E. Heath, Auditor of Public Accounts, corresponds with Governor Floyd regarding the debt due by Clement Townsend of New Orleans (1830 May 15), further allowance to Josiah Leake as agent for the Commonwealth in Goochland County (1830 June 30); flooring for the Treasury Office (1831 Apr. 23), an appropriation for compiling & publishing delinquent land lists (1831 Sept. 19), an advance for B. Smoot to convey a convict from Mason County (1831 Oct. 3), Boykin's claim for his service as brigade inspector (1832 Mar. 16), the publication of the revenue laws anterior to 1821 for distribution (1832 May 19), a letter from J. M. Patton transmitting an account for his services as counsel in the Superior Court of Orange (1832 Oct. 26), a certificate of public debt from L. C. Cantilon (1833 May 14), John H. Smith's letter requesting permission to use Revolutionary Land Bounty Warrants in the Capitol (1833 July 9), a new copy of the revised code (1832 Nov. 19), and receipt of the contract between Blair Bolling, J. B. Bragg, & William Bootwright to lease the Boring Mill, the bond of J. Bootwright as contractor to supply provisions for the Public Guard, and the bond of Thomas G. Moncure as agent & storekeeper of the Penitentiary (1834 Mar. 28).
  John H. Smith was initially appointed under an order of 24 May 1832 to examine & arrange the books & papers in the upper story of the Capitol. John H. Smith encloses a report of his proceedings in which he provides a description of the records found in the Capitol which includes Revolutionary War records, Henrico County Court records, & Auditor of Public Account's records (1832 July [N.D.]). Smith later writes regarding books & papers in his possession which may be useful to the members of the Council in deciding on claims for Revolutionary services (1832 Aug. 22). The General Assembly passed a resolution on 21 February 1833 that the Governor employ an individual to examine revolutionary documents and to report a list of the names of all such persons entitled to unsatisfied claims on the Commonwealth of Virginia for bounty land. John H. Smith was appointed as Commissioner of Revolutionary Claims to provide for the appointment of a commissioner to continue to examine and report upon these claims. Smith writes regarding Revolutionary claims (1833 July 25), his progress in the execution of the joint resolution concerning claims to military bounty land (1833 Oct. 14), his duties as agent for the state of Virginia to examine the claims of officers & soldiers of the Virginia Continental & State lines to military bounty lands (1833 Oct. 26), a report made to the U.S. Senate respecting officers & soldiers of the Revolutionary Army to bounty land (1833 Nov. 18), the claims of the heirs of Capt. William Gregory & Lt. John Gregory and the heirs of Brigadier General Hugh Mercer & Lt. Samuel Campbell (1834 Jan. 31), and petitions referred to him for bounty lands (1834 Feb. 10).
  Governors and secretaries from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor. This correspondence mostly relates to amendments to the U.S. Constitution, the militia, extraditions, the Tariff of 1828, and the Nullification Crisis. Included are letters from the following governors or secretaries: David Hazzard & Caleb Prew Bennett, Delaware; Jacques Dupre & Andre B. Roman, Louisiana; Edward Russell, Maine; Gideon Tomlinson & John S. Peters, Connecticut; Gabriel Moore, Alabama; Norman Williams, Vermont; Thomas Metcalfe, Kentucky; Daniel Martin & George Howard, Maryland; Duncan McArthur, Ohio; Levi Lincoln, Massachusetts; John Reynolds, Illinois; Montfort Stokes & David L. Swain, North Carolina; Samuel G. Smith, Tennessee; George Wolf, Pennsylvania; Robert Young Hayne, South Carolina; and Wilson Lumpkin, Georgia.
  Governors David Hazzard, Delaware, & Jacques Dupre, Louisiana, transmit resolutions in favor of the Tariff of 1828 (1830 Mar. 16 & Apr. 20). Governor Caleb Prew Bennett, Delaware, transmits a resolution against the resolution of South Carolina calling for a convention of the states to propose amendments to the Constitution (1833 Jan. 31). Bennett also transmits resolutions recommending a law by Congress providing for a more perfect & uniform organization of the militia of the several states (1833 Feb. 14). Governor Andre B. Roman, Louisiana, encloses resolutions regarding the survey of a contemplated railroad from the Mississippi River through the states of Louisiana, Mississippi, Tennessee, Virginia, Alabama, & North Carolina to Washington (1832 Apr. 30). Edward Russell, Secretary of State of Maine, transmits maps and statistical view of the State of Maine (1830 May 24). Governor Gideon Tomlinson, Connecticut, transmits a resolution concurring with the resolution of Missouri to amend the Constitution to provide a uniform mode of electing the president & vice president without the intervention of electors (1830 Aug. 28). Later, Governor John S. Peters transmits a report & resolutions as relates to the Constitution & judiciary of the U.S. (1831 June 30). Governor Gabriel Moore, Alabama, encloses a resolution recommending the re-election of Andrew Jackson as president (1830 Dec. 11). Norman Williams, Secretary of State of Vermont, transmits resolutions against the proposal of the state of Louisiana to amend the Constitution to extend the term of the office of the president & vice president to six years (1830 Dec. 10). Governor Thomas Metcalfe, Kentucky, transmits resolutions to open a road from Jonesborough, Tennessee, to the mouth of Shelly's Creek on the Big Sandy River (1830 Dec. 31). Governor Daniel Martin, Maryland, encloses a resolution for the opening of a safe & direct navigation through the sounds which run parallel with the coast (1831 Jan. 28). Afterward, Governor George Howard transmits resolutions against the re-election of Andrew Jackson and recommending Henry Clay as president (1832 June [N.D.]). Howard also writes respecting the boundary line between Virginia & Maryland (1832 June [N.D.]). Governor Duncan McArthur, Ohio, writes regarding the demand for a fugitive named Elton Conner (1831 Jan. 14). McArthur also writes regarding surveys of military lands by the Principal Surveyor of the Army Lands in the Virginia Military District (1831 July 1 & Nov. 15). Levi Lincoln, Massachusetts, transmits resolutions for a more perfect organization of the militia of the several states (1831 Mar. 9). Lincoln also transmits resolutions regarding the Constitution, judicial power, & laws of the U.S. (1831 Mar. 17). John Reynolds, Illinois, writes acknowledging receipt of a map of Virginia (1831 Mar. 14) and transmits resolutions for a law for the more perfect organization of the militia of the several states (1832 Dec. 22). Governor Montfort Stokes, North Carolina, writes regarding their publication of a declaration of independence by citizens of Mecklenburg County in May 1775 and other documents (1831 July 1). Stokes also writes regarding the demand for John Hickson, a fugitive from justice in Virginia (1831 Aug. 10). Subsequently, Governor David L. Swain, North Carolina, writes regarding the extradition of Washington Taborn, a fugitive from justice in Virginia (1833 Feb. 6), and a demand for Mark W. Jones confined in the jail of Norfolk County (1833 Nov. 18). Samuel G. Smith, Secretary of State of Tennessee, encloses a resolution relative to the public lands of the U.S. and a resolution in relation to the exercise of certain powers by the General Government (1832 Jan. 31). Governor George Wolf, Pennsylvania, transmits an act to open & improve part of the state road from Samuel Hills in Greene County, Pennsylvania, to Middlebourne, Virginia (1832 Jan. 24). Governor Robert Young Hayne, South Carolina, transmits resolutions for a convention of the states to consider & determine questions of disputed power between the states & general government (1833 Jan. 5). Hayne also transmits a copy of the reports & ordnances of the Convention of the people of South Carolina (enclosures not included) (1833 May 25). Lastly, Governor Wilson Lumpkin, Georgia, encloses a resolution against the resolutions of Tennessee in relation to the sale & disposition of the public lands of the United States (1834 Jan. 1).